## NUBIA A. CASTILLO de VALLE

Charlotte, NC 28273

954-536-6924 | nubiacastillo@gmail.com | Linkedin.com/in/nubiacastillo

### **Technology Business Leader**

Technology Executive with 20+ years of experience in information technology and business strategy. At Charter, communications managed budgets. Partnership management with developers, engineers, vendors, marketing, system integration, test, operations, beta management, go-to-market planning, developed product launch plans in partnership with marketing and sales, measuring product success through analytics and KPIs.

Delivered solutions at large scale customers 20 plus millions of subscribers, which contributed to Time Warner Cable growth from 2009 revenue of \$4.5 billion to 2016 the revenue rose to \$29.3 billion

Recently, I graduated from the University of North Carolina at Charlotte with a Doctor of Business Administration focused on strategy, technology, and research. My dissertation topic was strategy, Technology Adoption, Readiness for Change, and Organizational Resilience.

I am passionate about learning, utilizing knowledge and experience through collaboration to solve complex problems, and helping others.

### **Technology Management Skills**

Cloud Architecture (VMWare/AWS) | Cloud (IaaS, PaaS, SaaS) | Agile Methodologies | SDLC

Change Management | Product Development & Management | DevOps | I.T. Management Network Architecture & I.T. Security | Testing & Integration | Statistical Analysis | Business Strategy | Data Analytics | Vendor Management | Hiring, & Coaching Teams | Language skills (bilingual: English/Spanish)

### **Professional Experience**

# Director of Engineering, Charter Communications/Time Warner Cable, Charlotte, NC (2013-2017)

- I designed a business process to streamline and accelerate products to markets. I managed a team of expert systems engineers who drove the organization's product development using product roadmaps based on agile methodologies to promote collaboration with vendors and other crossfunctional teams. Partnered with internal business leaders and vendors to drive change, influence change, inspire other teams, increase morale, and deliver reliable and high-quality solutions. Recruited, hired, and built a talented team through coaching and collaboration.
- Defined priorities based on corporate strategy with product owners, architects, operations, thirdparty vendors, and developers. I outlined frameworks, forecasted and allocated resources, and created an inventory of existing and required skills to meet the new market demand. My team was responsible for complex enterprise-wide implementation projects (in a matrix organization, working with marketing, operations, customer service, implementation, and senior management).

### NUBIA A. CASTILLO de VALLE

Charlotte, NC 28273

954-536-6924 | nubiacastillo@gmail.com | Linkedin.com/in/nubiacastillo

It delivered high-quality solutions while meeting tight deadlines and budgets.

- Coached, mentored, and developed employees. As a result, my team contributed to a 4.9% revenue increase. In addition, I directed the creation and deployment of solutions in record time, resulting in a significant increase in customer satisfaction.
- Upgraded system verification turnaround 50% and achieved 95% system utilization with no downtime.
- Created a space of trust across a matrix organization and partnered with other teams to solve complex technical challenges. Conducted deep dives to understand the problems opportunities and re-align priorities and strategy as needed.
- Spearheaded disseminating technical information and training to developers, senior leaders, and marketing; documented and worked across organizations to deploy an improved application to market.

# Sr. Engineer Product Manager, Advanced Engineering Group, Time Warner Cable (2005-2013)

- Product manager and team leader skilled in all aspects of the product management life cycle, including uncovering market problems; driving product requirements through rapid prototyping and customer feedback; developing and presenting business cases; implementing new products and features using Agile development methodologies; managing beta programs; developing goto-market and launch plans in partnership with marketing and sales; measuring product success through analytics and KPIs.
- Product Manager of the digital video ecosystem for the Arris technology. The product lineup was up to twenty products and any new third-party integration with the digital video ecosystem (Arris/Motorola) cable technology. The Customer footprint of 20+ million subscribers.
- Actively supported growth, enhanced capabilities with engineering expertise, and provided leadership while revenue soared to \$4.5B with other 600K subscribers. Managed multiple concurrent projects.
- Achieved seamless integration of new solutions, collaborated across teams on installation, trained lab engineers, created configuration best practices, and documented integration of endto-end solutions.

### Systems Video Engineer, Advanced Engineering Group, Time Warner Cable (2003-2005)

- Managed the newly created lab's installation to mitigate the risk of deploying new technologies and accelerating products to the U.S. market.
- Configured ten cable systems in only four months. Worked with vendors, contractors, and crossfunctional teams and developed expertise in Motorola, Scientific Atlantic/Cisco, and third-party vendor technology.

Systems Engineer, Digital Latin America, Coral Springs, FL (2001–2003)

### NUBIA A. CASTILLO de VALLE

Charlotte, NC 28273

954-536-6924 | nubiacastillo@gmail.com | Linkedin.com/in/nubiacastillo

#### **Education**

Doctor of Business Administration (DBA), the University of North Carolina at Charlotte, NC, May 2021 (*cum laude*)

The DBA program at UNC Charlotte specializes in research methodology, statistical analysis, operations, information technology, marketing, management, leadership, entrepreneurship, and strategy. The dissertation topic for my doctorate was in design, precisely the drivers of organizational resilience in times of crisis (COVID-19). The context of change was the adoption and use of technology. The methodology was quantitative, and I used SMART-PLS and SPSS to perform the statistical analysis. The research suggests the antecedents that the proposed were significant at a p-value of 0.05. However, no causality can be inferred since it was a cross-sectional research model.

Master of Business Administration (MBA), Queens University of Charlotte, Charlotte, NC

Bachelor of Engineering (BE) in Electrical Engineer, John Brown University, Siloam Springs, AK

### **Certifications and Professional Development**

Executive Coaching Certification, Queens University of Charlotte, Charlotte, NC Project Management Plus Certificate Program, Central Piedmont Community College, Charlotte, NC Awards:

- Walton Academic Scholarship at John Brown University
- Entrepreneurship Award Winner at the McColl School of Business, Charlotte, NC
- Technology Risen Star, Women of Color STEM, NAMIC, Charlotte, NC

**Volunteer Experience:** Board member of the Time Warner Charlotte Diversity and Inclusion Committee; Jan 2009 - June 2017; Chairperson for a year in 2013

I served as a board chair of the Time Warner Diversity Council in Charlotte, NC. The diversity council developed initiatives such as inviting speakers and promoting a diverse culture week. These initiatives created awareness of how building teams of people with diverse experiences fosters innovation and improves overall performance.